"); } else { $mime_type = "text/html"; header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-90.3 Assignment 2

Reading

We are still working on material from Chapters 1 and 2 of the Simply JavaScript book, but have also started on the material in Chapter 3. We haven’t covered Objects, the last topic in Chapter 2 yet in class, but will be doing so next. We also haven’t covered conditions (if statements) and loops (for/while statements) yet; learn as much as you can about them from the text, because we will not spend a lot of class time on them despite their being critical parts of JavaScript.

The Assignment

Introduction

This is an exercise in working with various elements of the JavaScript language: literal values, variables, expressions, functions, and arrays. The emphasis of this assignment is on identifying types of information.

There are three parts to the assignment, just two of which are “deliverables” to be submitted for grading:

Write a JavaScript program to generate the answers to a sequence of questions (deliverable)
Use the Firebug console to view the output from your program (not deliverable).
Write out the answers to the questions for which your program generated the answers (deliverable).

Changes To Your Web Site

The only change to make to your index.xhtml file from Assignment 1 is to change the link to assignment_01.js into a link to another file named assignment_02.js.

Create the file assignment_02.js in your scripts directory, and add a sequence of statements to it that will generate the answers to the following list of questions.

Be sure the outputs from the program include the question numbers, as shown in the sample answers to the first two questions.

The Questions

I have provided you with the answer to the first two questions to provide models for doing the assignment.

What type of information is 3?

The code you write might look like this:

console.log("1. 3 is a " + typeof 3 + ".");

The program output should be 1. 3 is a number.—which would be the answer you type into your email for the first question.

Assign the value "3" to a variable named xanadu, and tell what type of information the variable holds.

var xanadu = "3"; console.log("2. xanadu is a " + typeof xanadu + ".");

The program output should be “2. xanadu is a string.”—which would be the answer you type for the second question.

Assign the value "3" + 3 to the same variable, xanadu, and tell what type of information the variable holds now.

Assign the value "3" - 3 to xanadu, and tell what type of information the variable holds now.

Explain the difference between the effects of the + and - operators in the previous two questions.

There is no JavaScript code to write for this question.

Assign the value 3 - xanadu to xanadu, and tell both the new value of xanadu and its type.

Assign the value 3 - "xanadu" to xanadu, and tell both the new value of xanadu and its type.

Explain the difference between the previous two questions.

There is no JavaScript code to write for this question.

Assign the value [ ] to a variable named Nan. What are the values and types of the variables, NaN, "NaN", and Nan?

Explain your answers.

What is the type of Nan?

Hint: the answer is not what you probably expected.

What value could you assign to Nan[0] so its type would be "number"?

What are the value and type of 1.23E2?

Assign the value function(){} to Nan[3]; tell the type of this value; tell the value of Nan.length.

What is the type of the value, { }?

Submit

When you have tested your code and determined the answers to the questions, type your answers into the body (not an attachment) of an email message, and send it to me. I’ll copy your entire web site to my computer (babbage) and check out your code and will check your email to be sure you answered the questions correctly.

Send your email message to me at: vickeryatbabbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu by midnight of the due date.

The Subject line of your email message must be: “CS-90.3 Assignment 2.”

Don’t forget to put your name in your email message!

Syllabus Schedule XHTML CSS Page last updated

"); } else { $mime_type = "text/html"; header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-90.3 Assignment 3

Reading

Read Chapter 3. Review any material you do not understand fully from Chapters 1-2.

The Assignment

Introduction

This assignment is an exercise in working with objects. The assignment is to prepare a script file that creates and displays the properties of various objects.

Replace all links to scripts in your index.xhtml page with a new link to a single script file named scripts/assignment_03.js. Create that file, and edit statements into it as you work through the assignment steps.

I’m reluctant to give the following advice because, in general, it is better to pay attention to warning messages rather than to ignore them. But in preparing this assignment I got really tired of all the blue warning messages that were coming out on the Firebug console. Clicking on the dropdown menu of the Console tab and un-checking the “Show JavaScript Warnings” option really helped.

Assignment Steps

Create an empty object named cs903 in the global object.

First, prove that the variable named cs903 is undefined by using console.log statments to print the type of both cs903 and window.cs903. (We will explore the window object below.)

Then without using the var keyword, assign the value { } to variable named cs903.

To improve the clarity of this assignment’s output, display a copy of each assignment statement just before executing it. That is, the first four lines of your script file should be:

console.log("The type of cs903 is '" + typeof cs903 + "'."); console.log("The type of window.cs903 is '" + typeof window.cs903 + "'."); console.log("cs903 = { };"); cs903 = { };

Now repeat the first two console.log() statements to display the type of cs903 and window.cs903 again.

Verify that before the assignment statement, both cs903 and window.cs903 are undefined, but after the assignment they are both objects.

Write out the answers to the following questions in the email you submit for this assignment:

What is the type of a variable before it is assigned a value?
Is it necessary to use the var keyword to define a variable?
If you don’t use the var keyword to define a variable, where is that variable created?
What is the type of the variable named window?
Why is window called the “global object”?

Turn the cs903 variable into a function and execute it.

Add code to assignment_03.js to assign the value function(){ console.log("This is window.cs903"); } to the global variable cs903. Add console.log() statements to document the assignment statement and to show the new type of window.cs903.

Add statements to execute your new function:

cs903(); window.cs903();

You should see the message, “This is window.cs903” displayed twice.

Repeat the previous step for another function, named onload()

This really is the same as the previous steps, except you can skip the part about assigning an object to the property you will use here, the window.onload property. Display the type of onload and window.onload, then assign a function to it that displays the message, “This is window.onload” (instead of “This is window.cs903”), when the function executes.

Run your code, and write out answers to the following questions:

What was the type of the window.onload property before you assigned a value to it?
Anything different from using cs903 yet?
What was the type of the window.onload property after you assigned the function to it?
Anything different from using cs903 yet?
How many times did the “This is window.onload” message appear?
What is different from using cs903?
Explain the difference.

Submit

When you have tested your code and determined the answers to the questions, type your answers into the body (not an attachment) of an email message, and send it to me. I’ll copy your entire web site to my computer (babbage) and check out your code and will check your email to be sure you answered the questions correctly.

Send your email message to me at: vickeryatbabbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu by midnight of the due date.

The Subject line of your email message must be: “CS-90.3 Assignment 3.”

Don’t forget to put your name in your email message!

Syllabus Schedule XHTML CSS Page last updated

"); } else { $mime_type = "text/html"; header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-90.3 Assignment 4

Reading

Read Chapter 7.

The Assignment

Introduction

This assignment is an exercise in working with objects, functions, conditionals, and loops. As in the previous two assignments, you are to prepare a script file that demonstrates features of JavaScript and answers some questions.

Replace all links to scripts in your index.xhtml page with a new link to a single script file named scripts/assignment_04.js. Create that file, and edit statements into it as you work through the assignment steps.

Assignment Steps

Create a function that receives one parameter and displays the parameter’s type.

Name the function foo(). You may do it either of two ways

foo = function(param) { console.log("foo: param is of type '" + typeof param + "'."); };

or

function foo(param) { console.log("foo: param is of type '" + typeof param + "'."); }

There is a difference between the two: the first technique defines the function when the assignment to foo takes place. The second one defines the function as soon as the script is loaded by the browser. If you wanted to you, you could put the second type of function definition at the end of the script file, and still use it at the beginning.

For this assignment, you need to keep re-defining foo(), so except for the first time you define the function, you will have to use the assignment statement form. For the first definition you could use either form.

When the function is defined, call it five times, passing it the following values:

{ }
[ ]
123
"1"
foo

Explain each of the five lines of output.

Redefine foo() so it recognizes arrays and objects.

The goal is to get one of the following messages to print out, depending on what is passed as an argument to foo() when it is called.

foo: param is an array
foo: param is an object
foo: param is neither an array nor an object

For example, for the five calls in the first step, the messages should be:

foo: param is an object foo: param is an array foo: param is neither an array nor an object foo: param is neither an array nor an object foo: param is neither an array nor an object

For this assignment, you may simply make the assumption that if an object has a length property, it is an array. You should know by now that it is possible to add any property to any object, so this test is not foolproof. But we will not try to make fools of ourselves!

To do this step, you will have to use if statements (textbook pages 36-43). I’m giving you the hard part, telling if the parameter is an array. You have to add the else and else if parts to make it a three-way decision.

foo = function(param) { if ( (typeof param === "object") && (typeof param.length === "number") ) { console.log("foo: param is an array"); } else { console.log("foo: param is not an array"); } }

Redefine foo() so it sums numerical elements if the parameter is an array.

For both parts of this step, use for loops. There is an example of using a for loop to double all the elements in an array on page 47 of the textbook. Here is the code to sum all the elements in an array:

var numbers = [ 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, -16 ]; var sum = 0; for (var i = 0; i < numbers.length; i++) { sum = sum + numbers[i]; } console.log("The sum is " + sum + ".");

Note that it is very important to initialize the variable sum before looping through the numbers.

The statement inside the loop could have been written using the shorthand, sum += numbers[i]; if you want to save a little typing.

But for this assignment, you have to test each element of the array to be sure it is a number:

if (typeof param[i] === "number") sum += param[i];

The body of an if statement does not have to be inside curly braces if there is only one statement. In the above example, the braces are omitted and the single statement is moved to the same line as the if test. Never omit the braces when putting a single statement body on a separate line: it almost always leads to errors later on.

You can use the following lines of code to test your function:

console.log("foo([100, 20, 3, 'hello']);"); foo([100, 20, 3, 'hello']); console.log("foo({a:100, b:'20', c:20, d:3});"); foo({a:100, b:'20', c:20, d:3}); console.log("foo(123);"); foo(123); console.log("foo('1');"); foo('1'); console.log("foo(foo);"); foo(foo);

Add code to foo() so it sums the numeric properties of objects.

Use a different kind of for loop to do this. JavaScript has a special type of for loop for iterating over the properties of an object, but it is not covered in the textbook. Here is an example of it in action:

var obj = { a:3, b:5, c:"hello", a_long_property_name:7 }; for (var property_name in object) { console.log("obj." + property_name + " has the value " + obj[property_name]); }

I’ll explain this below, but it’s good enough if you can see the pattern in the example and adapt it to the assignment. After you have updated the function, use the same set of function calls to test it. You should see the sum for the numeric property values as well as the sum of the numeric array elements.

Gory Details

This type of for loop assigns the name of each property in an object, as a string, to the loop variable (property_name in the example) on each iteration. You may recall that we could use strings and negative numbers as subscripts for arrays, but that those elements don’t count in the length of the array. You may also recall that arrays are actually objects. Putting it all together, if you use a non-negative integer subscript, you can assign values to the “array part” of an array, but if you use negative integers (or non-integers, like 1.2) or stings as a subscript, you are using the “object part” of an array with the added twist that the subscript values do not have to be valid property names; if they are not strings, they get converted to strings. And you can use variables holding the string representations of these property names as subscripts!

This is a rather obscure topic at this point. But being able to iterate over the properties of an object can be a very useful debugging technique that you can use even if you don’t understand exactly how it works.

Here is some sample code and the output it generates. (Math is an object built into JavaScript that has a property named PI that holds the value of the mathematical constant, π.)

var a = [ 1, 2, 'hello']; a[-1] = 123; a[Math.PI] = "I like apple"; a['something'] = 321; for (p in a) { console.log("p is a " + typeof p + " and its value is '" + p + "'. a[p] is " + a[p]); } console.log("a.something is " + a.something); console.log("a['something'] is " + a['something']); console.log("The length of array a is " + a.length); --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- p is a string and its value is '0'. a[p] is 1 p is a string and its value is '1'. a[p] is 2 p is a string and its value is '2'. a[p] is hello p is a string and its value is '-1'. a[p] is 123 p is a string and its value is '3.141592653589793'. a[p] is I like apple p is a string and its value is 'something'. a[p] is 321 a.something is 321 a['something'] is 321 The length of array a is 3

Check your program’s output.

It should look like this, but without the step number messages:

Step 1

foo([ ]); foo: param is of type 'object'. foo({ }); foo: param is of type 'object'. foo(123); foo: param is of type 'number'. foo('1'); foo: param is of type 'string'. foo(foo); foo: param is of type 'function'.

Step 2

foo([ ]); foo: param is an array foo({ }); foo: param is an object foo(123); foo: param is neither an array nor an object foo('1'); foo: param is neither an array nor an object foo(foo); foo: param is neither an array nor an object

Steps 3 and 4

foo([100, 20, 3, 'hello']); foo: param is an array foo: the sum of the numeric elements in the array is: 123 foo({a:100, b:'20', c:20, d:3}); foo: param is an object foo: param.a is of type 'number' foo: param.b is of type 'string' foo: param.c is of type 'number' foo: param.d is of type 'number' foo: The sum of the numeric properties is 123 foo(123); foo: param is neither an array nor an object foo('1'); foo: param is neither an array nor an object foo(foo); foo: param is neither an array nor an object

Submit

When you have tested your code and determined the answers to the questions, type your answers into the body (not an attachment) of an email message, and send it to me. I’ll copy your entire web site to my computer (babbage) and check out your code and will check your email to be sure you answered the questions correctly.

Send your email message to me at: vickeryatbabbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu by midnight of the due date.

The Subject line of your email message must be: “CS-90.3 Assignment 4.”

Don’t forget to put your name in your email message!

Syllabus Schedule XHTML CSS Page last updated

"); } else { $mime_type = "text/html"; header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-90.3 Assignment 6

Overview and Preparation

This is the same as Assignment 5, but implemented using CSS rules and class attributes rather than direct manipulation of the style properties of the paragraphs in the DOM tree.

Create a new script file, assignment_06.js, to replace the script file you used for Assignment 5.

You can use the same stylesheet as for Assignment 5, but add the following rules to it:

.happy { color:red; } .sad { color:blue; } .envious { color: green; } .excited { font-style:italic; }

The idea is for various sequences of mouseover and mouseout events to cause the paragraphs to change color and font-style by manipulating each paragraph's class attribute. Each time the user mouses over a paragraph, it’s class is to change to the next class in the sequence happy, envious, and sad. In addition, the paragraph’s class is to alternate between excited and not on alternate mouseover events.

Unlike Assignment 5, the state of each paragraph is not to change when there are mouseout events. That is, assignment_06.js will not have a mouseoutHandler() function.

The Assignment

Set up the mouseover event handler for this assignment.

Create a window.onload event handler function the way you did for Assignment 5, and add a function named mouseoverHandler to it, again, the way you did for Assignment 5. Set this function up as the mouseover event handler for all the paragraphs in the document. Temporarily insert a console.log() function call that prints a simple message, such as “mouseover” and verify that the message is displayed each time you move your mouse over any paragraph in the web page.

Add the class management functions from the textbook.

Add three more functions to the onload event handler function: hasClass(), addClass(), and removeClass(). The code for these three functions is given on pages 383—384. Note that you will need to change each function definition so the functions are defined in your onload function instead of the (nonexistent) Core object assumed to exist by the textbook. For example, the first line of hasClass() on page 384 is:

Core.hasClass = function(target, theClass)

But you need to change the above line to:

function hasClass(target, theClass)

Implement the font-style changes.

Remove the console.log() statement from the mouseover event handler.

In the mouseover event handler, use the hasClass() function to see whether the paragraph the mouse moved over is excited or not. If it is not, add that class to it; if it is, remove that class from it.

Test your web page, and verify that each paragraph changes to italic or back each time the mouse moves over it.

Implement the color changes.

Add more code to the mouseover handler so that each paragraph changes its emotional state based on whether it is currently happy, envious, or sad.

Test your web page carefully to make sure the emotional and excitedness of each paragraph has been fully controlled by your JavaScript program.

Submit

When you are sure your program does everything correctly, and that there are no errors are warnings from the XHTML and CSS validators, nor from Firebug, just send me an email message, and I’ll check it out in the usual way.

Send your email message to me at: vickeryatbabbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu by midnight of the due date.

The Subject line of your email message must be: “CS-90.3 Assignment 6.”

Don’t forget to put your name in your email message!

Syllabus Schedule XHTML CSS Page last updated

"); } else { $mime_type = "text/html"; header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-90.3 Assignment 9

Requirement

Add functionality to Assignment 8 so that the response to submitting the form is one of three messages:

User, _____, not found.
User, _____, found, but your password, _____, is incorrect. It should be _____.
Welcome, _____, thank you for logging in!

The Assignment

Prepare your database.

Use a spreadsheet program such as OpenOffice Calc, Microsoft Excel, or Apple Numbers to create a table with two columns. Put a list of email addresses in the first column, and a set of corresponding passwords in the second column. You may use real email addresses, but be sure the passwords are all fictional! Include 4-5 rows in your table.

Create a directory named db in your web site, and save your spreadsheet there as a CSV (comma separated values) document.

Use PHP to display your database.

Use the PHP fopen() function to open your database file, and then use a while loop to read each line in the file using the fgetcsv() function, generating a table row in your web page for each line in the file.

Open the file. Save the value returned by fopen() in a meaningfully-named variable, such as $user_database_connection. I am purposely using a long variable name as an example to encourage you to think of a name that would be equally meaningful but easier to type!
Here is how to read lines from a file until they all have been read:

while ($row = fgetcsv($user_database_connection)) { // Process each line from the file here }

Your job is to replace the comment line in the above sample code with PHP statements that will echo a table row with two cells in it, which you are to fill with the values of $row[0] and $row[1].

Be sure your page generate the proper start tag for the table before the loop, and the proper end tag after the end of it. There should also be a header row before the first data row.

Use CSS to style the table so it is easy to read.

Implement the Assignment.

Now that you have established that you can process the information in the database file, use if, else if, and else to implement the following algorithm:

Set a variable (conventionally named, $found) to false.
Reset the database file to the beginning. After going through the loop that generates the table of database contents, you can reposition the file so you can read it all over again by using the fseek() function like this: fseek($user_database_connection, 0);
Loop through the lines in the database file, comparing the first element to the value of the username from the form. If there is a match:

Set $found to true.
If the password value from the form matches the second element from the database row, generate the third message (“Welcome… ”), and use a break statement to exit from the loop. Fill in the blank with the user’s name.

Optional: You can use the === operator to compare strings for equality, but this is a case-sensitive comparison. If you want to let the user name be case-insensitive, the easiest way is to use PHP’s strcasecmp() function, which returns the value 0 if two strings passed as arguments are equal, ignoring upper/lower case differences. Do not use this function for checking passwords!

If the password value does not match the second element from the database row, generate the second message listed above. Again, use a break statment to exit the loop. Fill in the first blank with the name of the user submitted from the form, the second blank with the password submitted from the form, and the third blank with the value of the second value in the row from the database.

After the end of the loop, test the value of $found: if it is not true, echo the first message above. Fill in the blank with the user name submitted from the form.

Use CSS to make everything beautiful!

Submit

When you are sure your program does everything correctly, and that there are no errors are warnings from the XHTML and CSS validators, nor from Firebug, just send me an email message, and I’ll check it out in the usual way.

Send your email message to me at: vickeryatbabbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu by midnight of the due date.

The Subject line of your email message must be: “CS-90.3 Assignment 9.”

Don’t forget to put your name in your email message!

Syllabus Schedule XHTML CSS Page last updated